<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly sermon preached at Detford in Kent, on Monday the ix. of Iune, in Anno. 1572.</title>
            <author>Pagit, Eusebius, 1547?-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1586</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08819</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19105</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105805</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841531</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841531</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6120</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08819)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6120)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1324:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly sermon preached at Detford in Kent, on Monday the ix. of Iune, in Anno. 1572.</title>
                  <author>Pagit, Eusebius, 1547?-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. 1586.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Eusebius Pagit.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C.</note>
                  <note>Slight print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6120:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6120:1"/>
            <p>A GODLY SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: <hi>Preached at Detford</hi> in Kent, on Monday the ix. of Iune, in Anno. 1572.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON, <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>Printed for Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Man. An.</hi> 1586.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:6120:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6120:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Godly Sermon, Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched</hi> at Detford in Kent.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Text.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1. Cor. 7. ver. 1.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>NOw coneerning the thinges wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ye wrote vnto me.
It were good for a man not to touch a woman.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <bibl>ver. 2.</bibl>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Neuertheleſſe to auoid fornication let euery man haue his wife,
and let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry woman haue her own Husband.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, thrée perſons &amp; one God, let vs pray. O gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God, and moſt mercifull Father, by whoſe goodneſſe it commeth to paſſe, that wee haue bene ſafely preſerued from our yong &amp; ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:6120:3"/>yeres vnto this preſent houre: &amp; are now called together to ſerue thée, by ſin ging of Pſalmes, with preaching and prayer: we moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſéech thée for thy ſon chriſts ſake, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou wilt not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our minds to be negligentlye wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering about other matters, to make thée more and more diſpleaſed agaynſt vs: but ſo to order &amp; gouern the ſame, by the inſpiration of thy holy ſpirit, that we may by theſe vertuous excerciſes, learn more &amp; more to mortifie &amp; kil the luſts of the fleſh, to ſorrow and lament our ſinful wretchednes &amp; miſery, and to repent and ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d our liues in ſuch ſort, as all may redound to the kingdome of Chriſt, and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> confuſion of Antichriſt, to the ſetting vp of his glory, and to the pulling downe, &amp; cleane ouerthrowing of al ſuperſtition, falſe doctrine, hereſie and popery: thorow the ſame thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IT is written in the vij. Chapter of the firſt Epiſtle of S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> in the beginning of the Chapter in theſe wordes: <hi>Nowe concerning the things whereof you wrote vnto me, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6120:3"/>For the better vnderſtanding of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles mind, we haue to conſider, that (after the Apoſtle had preached thegoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and planted a Church amongſt them, &amp; was gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to publiſhe the glad tidinges of ſaluation to others alſo, for he was not then (as Preachers at this preſent ſhould be) tyed to one flock: but by the vertue of his commiſſion hee muſt goe thorow all the worlde) falſe Apoſtles entred into the Churche, who being puffed vp with vaine glorye, and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate eloquence, ſought to bring into contempt, the ſimplicity whiche <hi>Paule</hi> vſed in preaching the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Here in the very entraunce we haue two things to learne. Firſt, that as God is willing, and woulde haue all men ſaued, and come to the knowledge of his truth, and therefore vſeth meanes to accompliſh it, namely the preaching of his goſpell, which is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> power of god to ſaluation to all that beléeue. So our common aduerſary the Diuell, goeth about like a roaring lion, not onely ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in himſelfe to deuour vs, but alſo
<pb facs="tcp:6120:4"/>vſing his inſtruments to deceiue vs,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.1. 2. Tim. 3.1. 1. Peter. 3.3. Iud. 18. Mat. 23.24</note> &amp; to draw vs backward into al error and ſuperſtition. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly we may here ſée, what a gap is opened to all inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, when y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Miniſter or Preacher is from among his flocke. <hi>Paul</hi> no ſooner gon from <hi>Corinthus</hi> but by and by falſe Apoſtles labour to deſtroy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which hée had pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 1.10.</note> He was no ſooner departed from the churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> but there craftilye crept in falſe brethren, that corrupted the pure doctrine of Chriſt, and taught that the ceremonies of the law muſt be neceſſarily obſerued.
<note place="margin">Exod. 32.2.</note> 
               <hi>Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> no ſooner gone vp into the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to receaue the law at the Lords ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, but the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fall by and by to Idolatrye and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe. And <hi>Paul</hi> ſéemeth to warne the elders of <hi>Epheſus</hi> concerning this matter alſo,
<note place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> when he ſayth: Take héede therefore vnto your ſelues and to all the flocke, whereof the holy Ghoſt hath made you ouerſéers, to féede the church of God, which he hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with his owne blood. For I knowe this, that after my departure ſhal grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous
<pb facs="tcp:6120:4"/>wolues enter in among you, not ſparing the flock, O that our <hi>Non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents</hi> would but conſider this: O that they which giue them liberty to ſinne, would weigh this, then mens conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhould not be ſo clogged with ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie &amp; vngodlines as they are. Then gods people ſhould be better inſtructed fed &amp; loked vnto, in reſpect of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual paſture, than eyther nowe they are, or hitherto haue ben. God in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy if it be his will and pleaſure bring it to paſſe. But to returne, theſe falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles that had thruſt in themſelues, among the <hi>Corinthians</hi> after <hi>Paules</hi> departure, did not onelye as before I ſayd, bring into diſliking, <hi>Paules</hi> plain and ſimple kinde of teaching, but alſo indeuoured to intangle with vayne and fooliſhe queſtions, the mindes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and albeit the <hi>Corinthians</hi> did harken much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: yet it appeareth that they did not vtterly ſhake off that authority and credit which they had of <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they demaunded Pauls iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t concerning ſuch matters, as the falſe
<pb facs="tcp:6120:5"/>Apoſtles and Preachers went about to perſwade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in: &amp; here by the way one thing is taught to you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you receaue not as truth euery thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery one ſpeaketh, for all is not golde that gliſtereth, but try the ſpirits whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be of God, yea or no, &amp; agayn: proue all things, but retaine only ſuche things as be good, you haue for your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this behalfe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of our Saniour Chriſt, ſearch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: &amp; alſo that notable example of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> who receiued the word with all readines, &amp; ſearched the ſcriptures dayly whether theſe thinges were ſo. The queſtions which the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> propoſed, were (as may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be proued by the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances of this chapter) concerning ſingle life, the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of mariage. Beſides of diſcord &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in mariage, of mariage between y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful &amp; vnfaithful, of vncircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſing the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eiſed of ſeruitude, of virginity, &amp; ſecond mariage. Of all theſe at this preſent it is impoſſible to ſpeak. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will deale only with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two firſt, that is concerning ſingle life, and the
<pb facs="tcp:6120:5"/>dueties of married folke, of which two poyntes the Apoſtle doeth largely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 9 firſt verſes of this chapter. To deale with any other curious diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the text, I minde not, for that I ſee it wil be the more profitable for you, the more ſimply I deale herein: I will therefore take the words as they lye, and expound them, briefly withall: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuering vnto you, ſuch obſeruations of doctrine and chriſtian inſtructions, as God by his ſpirit ſhall reueale vnto me. In the beginning of my text, are theſe wordes. <hi>Now concerning the thinges &amp;c.</hi> The Apoſtle had in ſome of the Chapters before goyng, and eſpecially in the latter end of the <hi>6.</hi> Chapter, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of a certaine diſeaſe, named fornication: for this ſicknes he appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in this Chapter a double remedie: the one is marriage made in the feare of God: the other is the gifte of chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: or ſole life proceeding from God. The Apoſtle ſaith that the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> did write vnto him about certaine matters. By whiche it maye bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, that it was a cuſtome in thoſe dayes, when darke and doubtful cauſes
<pb facs="tcp:6120:6"/>did ariſe, by wryting to demaund the iudgement of the diſciples &amp; apoſtles of Chriſt: who being taken out of this life, afterwards they went for counſaile to holy Biſhoppes and learned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which cuſtome as it was commendable, ſo being abuſed, it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred a certayne tyrannie. For the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> (whoſe iudgement was ſundry times aſked) began by that meanes, to vſurpe Lordſhippe and rule ouer the congregations of Chriſt, as as though nothing ought to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſubſtantiall and true without his aduiſe, a very proude and ambitious kind of dealing. But let that paſſe. It is moſt ſure that the <hi>Corinthians</hi> did write vnto him, and wee haue the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and matter of their queſtions: yet concerning the manner and forme thereof, there is muche controuerſie. Lord God what a ſtirre <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Hierome</hi> do in that behalfe keepe. It ſhall be ſuperfluous to rehearſe their ſayinges and reaſons, for that they make adoe where none needeth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the time may beſpent in more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb facs="tcp:6120:6"/>and profitable matter. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, to reaſon of thinges doubtefull, when we haue thinges certayne &amp; ſure before our eyes, is meere vanitie and ſmacketh ſomewhat of fooliſhnes. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in theſe words we haue for our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to marke: firſt, the willingnes of the people, and the deſire that they had to be inſtructed in matters of truth and religion, &amp; therefore ſent to <hi>Paul</hi> their queſtions, requeſting to haue his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweares thereto. Secondly, the great care that <hi>Paul</hi> had to doe good to all maner of men by all meanes poſſible, who beſide that he had taught them in his preſence, doth nowe notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as a token of the continuance of his good will towards them, inſtructe them alſo in his abſence by wryting. If we nowe apply this to our tyme &amp; age, and compare our miniſters &amp; people, with this people and their preacher, we ſhall find as great oddes and as much difference as is betwixt white &amp; black. For (that I may deale firſt with the people, they had ſome knoweledge of God:) ours altogether want knowledg
<pb facs="tcp:6120:7"/>of God and godlineſſe: they laboured to increaſe in all knoweledge: wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in all ignorance and darkenes: and if any would reach vs his hand, to drawe vs out of the filth and myre of ſinne, we account him our greateſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, There was amongeſt them, by reaſon of diſcipline, ſeuere puniſhment of ſinne: and by that meanes alſo god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines of life and holines of conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for lacke of it among vs, the bridle is giuen to all maner of iniquitie, and all kind of vngratiouſnes and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, doth without puniſhment rule &amp; raigne amongſt vs. Now concerning the miniſter, he preached vnto them: ours reade to vs, and ſcarſe that, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to knowledge: hee profiteth them both by preaching and writing: ours neyther of thoſe wayes doe any good: be able to teach, and that which hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of others, was in himſelfe, for he was able to ſtoppe the mouthes of the aduerſaries: ours are for the moſt part, blinde guydes, ſleepie watchmen, dumbe dogges, and as the Prophete <hi>Zacharie</hi> rightly calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, idle ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heardes, nay rather Idols themſelues.
<pb facs="tcp:6120:7"/>For they haue a mouth and ſpeake not, they haue eyes &amp; ſee not, they haue ears and heare not, they haue noſes and ſmel not: they haue handes &amp; touch not, they haue feete and walke not, neyther make they a ſound with their throat: they that make them are like vnto them, and ſo are all that truſt in them. A lamentable caſe, that they that ſhould guide other, are themſelues to be guided, becauſe they be blinde: and that they that ſhould leade other, are ſo lame, that they can not goe on their feete: nay I woulde to God there were not, that to the lacke of knowledge in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, adde innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable heaps of vices: ſome ruffians, ſome whoremo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers &amp; drunkards, ſome blaſphemers, &amp; ſome ſpotted with this publike crime, ſome with that, whereby they not only purchaſe vnto themſelues an euil report and rumor to goe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo cauſe Gods name &amp; his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to be euill ſpoken of. So that you may ſee how farre our mintſters are off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being like <hi>Paul,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ought in this caſe, &amp; other poynts alſo to follow as far forth as by Gods ſpirit they ſhal be aſſeſſed: but as there is no agreement
<pb facs="tcp:6120:8"/>betwixt light and darkenes: ſo there is not in any reſpecte almoſt any likenes betwixte him and them: agayne, 'where as <hi>Paul</hi> if his iudgement were aſked, concerning matters of faith and religt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was able to giue ſound and ſincere iudgement, according as Gods trueth, which alſo is required in euery one that taketh vpon him the office &amp; name of a mimſter, theſe in ſuch caſes are ſo farre off from executing any parte of their function, that you were with the <hi>Romanes</hi> as good goe to the geeſe of the Capitall of <hi>Rome,</hi> or els with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> aſke counſell at your ſtocks, and haue your ſtaffe teach you. Marry in deede if you deale with them for kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping a gelding or a hawke, for dreſſing a garden, orchard or bowling alley, for tabling or carding, or any ſuch other fooliſhnes and vanitye, they will &amp; can behaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues moſt cunningly: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would I haue any to gather here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, that in a generalitie I condemne all, For I knowle that in this realme, there are many both godly and learned my meaning is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the greateſt number
<pb facs="tcp:6120:8"/>and common ſort are ſuch, as continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all experience at this day to the great griefe and ſorrowe of the godly, too too plainely declareth. The Lord put into the harte of Prince and Magiſtrates, to remoue theſe, and (if it bee his will) to ſee ſuch placed in his vyneyard, as may haſten in his harueſt. But to let this paſſe, and to intreat of thoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which ſpecially concerne the cauſe for which we are at this preſent aſſembled. The Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>It were good for a man, not to touch a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi> The meaning is not, that mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage by Gods inſtitution is euill or wicked: for that were intollerable blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie if any ſhoulde ſo ſay: but that marriage, becauſe thorowe mans cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions it bringeth cares &amp; troubles, is not expedient, I iudge this worde <hi>(good)</hi> to bee taken (not as <hi>Ierome</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Iouinian</hi> taketh it, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche is contrarie and againſt euill, as he too childiſhly and peeuiſhly, by the leaue of ſo great a father doeth take it, and as <hi>Tertullian</hi> (ſomewhat before him did take the ſame alſo,) but for expedient &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:6120:9"/>profitable, as in other places of the ſcripture, it is lykewiſe vſed. And this rule of <hi>Paul</hi> is to be vnderſtood of ſuch, as vpon whom the Lord hath beſtowed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gift of chaſtitie, not only of bodie but alſo of minde. For albeit there are ſome good interpreters, that apply it gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to thoſe three kind of <hi>Eunuches,</hi> or chaſte perſons, whereof our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt ſpeaketh, yet am not I of that mind, becauſe that many otherwiſe chaſt in body, haue not with ſtanding their minds &amp; vnderſtanding defiled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vunatural luſts &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcence, which before our God is a great &amp; a greuous ſinne. So then <hi>Paul</hi> addreſſeth himſelfe in this place to ſpeake to ſuch as haue pure hearts and clean bodies, which is either hardly or not at all found in any. For who can ſay, my hearte is cleane before God, and this may playnely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto vs by that which followeth. <hi>Neuertheleſſe, to auoyd fornication, let euery man haue his wife, and let euery woman haue her own huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi> and againe, <hi>if they can not abſtaine, let them marrie, for it is better to
<pb facs="tcp:6120:9"/>marrie, then to burne.</hi> To make this more plaine by a ſimilitude, If one ſhould ſay after this maner: <hi>It is good for a man neither to eate, to drinke, nor to ſleepe:</hi> vnleſſe he were well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, he ſhould appeare to ſpeake very abſurdely, becauſe he ſeemeth to take away all ſuch neceſſaries, as whereby God hath appointed mans life to be mainteined: yet the partie ſo ſaying, doth not diſprayſe meat and drinke, and ſleepe, as things noyſome and hurtfull, but meaneth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould liue more godly, if being freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe prouocations, we gaue our ſelues who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſideration of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly things. For more then the competent and néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſufficing of our nature, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is giuen vnto theſe, is dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from the ſpirit. Euen ſo the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doth not condemne marriage in this ſaying, as euill or wicked, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many lettes and ſtops are found in fleſhly marriages, he ſaith <hi>It were good not to be married,</hi> for that doth hee vnderſtand by touching of a woman, as the beſt &amp; moſt learned expoſitors y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I
<pb facs="tcp:6120:10"/>ſeene take it. It followeth, <hi>Neuertho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, for the auoyding of fornication, &amp;c.</hi> In theſe words the Apoſtle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth ſuch as are vnchaſt, to run to the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God hath appointed: for although the ſentence ſeeme to be vniuerſall, yet it oght to be reſtrained vnto them, who feele themſelues by a certaine needful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be pricked forward. In this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe no law can be preſcribed, neither can we iudge one of another, but euery man ſhould bee a ſufficient witneſſe to himſelfe, becauſe in himſelfe he feeleth the infirmities and prickes of the fleſh. and albeit there appeareneuer ſo many ſtops &amp; lets in marriage, yet this muſt all vnderſtand, to whom God hath not giuen the gift of chaſtitie (and and ſo by that meanes not able to withſtand the prickes of the fleſh) that this comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement is by the Lord layde vpon their ſhoulders as a burden to beare, which if it be not performed (feeing that God hath appointed this as a remedie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne) they commit grieuos ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and by that their dealing heape vnto themſelues wrath agaynſt the day
<pb facs="tcp:6120:10"/>of the Lord. Moreouer the place of the Apoſtle muſt not be ſo vnderſtoode, as though this were the onely cauſe, why marriages ſhould be made, but this is his drift, not ſomuch to ſhew for what cauſes marriage was orderned, as for what perſons it was fit and neceſſarie, for if we haue reſpect vnto the time of the firſt inſtitution, it could not be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doſe aſe which yet was not (I meane ſin) but it was ordeyned for the procreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of children, the increaſe of mankind, and the mutuall ſocietie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the one ſhould haue of the other: &amp; after mans fal the ſecond vſe was added. To ſtand vpon the tearmes. <hi>fornication &amp; adulterie,</hi> &amp; the differences betwixt them, we ſhall not neede, becauſe it is more curious then neceſſary, &amp; this we ſee, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſcripture doth as wel vſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one as the other tearm, in many places, for all quchaſt &amp; vnſober behauiour of our ſelues, either in bodie or mind. This is inough out of this place to be gathered, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> though the world make little account of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting ſuch wickednes, yet it is a great ſin before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maieſty of god, which
<pb facs="tcp:6120:11"/>euidently appeareth, becauſe hee will haue thoſe that are his, to ſhun and flye from the ſame. If this be not ſufficient, caſt but your eies vp to the latter end of the former chapiter, and ſee how hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous a crime the Apoſtle maketh it: there he warneth them to flee fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the reaſon whereby he would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them from that ſinne, is taken from the notoriouſnes and grieuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the fact. For ſayth he, <hi>euery ſinne that a man doeth, is without the body: but be that committteth fornication, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noth against his owne bodie,</hi> that is to ſay, he more pollineth his owne bodie, then he that committeth any other ſin. If this will not ſerue, haue an eye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe puniſhments which God hath appointed vnto thoſe wicked contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and breakers of his ordinaunces, His puniſhments are two folde, eyther temporall or perpetuall. The perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall puniſhment of God, is that bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning lake of fire and brimſtone, which is prepared for the diuill &amp; his angels, where ſhalbe weeping, wayling, and gnaſhing of teeth, without (fayth <hi>Iohn</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6120:11"/>in his reuelation) <hi>ſhall be dogs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunters, and whoremongers, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, and idolaters, and whoſoeuer lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and maketh lyes:</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Know ye not that the vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous ſhall not inherite the kingdome of God. Be not deceiued, neither fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor buggerers, nor thieues, nor couetous, nor drunkards, nor-raylers, nor extortioners ſhall inherit the kingdome of God:</hi> which places are to be vnderſtood of ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men, as are the ſeruants of ſin, and ſold to worke wickednes, &amp; die in the ſame w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out harty and vnfaigned re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. His temporall puniſhments are alſo of two ſortes: eyther in thoſe which he layeth vpon the committers of ſuch wickednes, of himſelfe: as war, plagues, peſtilences, ſickenes, pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; ſuch like, which bring his children to a conſideration of their faultes, and a beholding of his mercie, but haue in the wicked and reprobate a contrarie effect and operation. and in the <hi>26.</hi> of <hi>Geneſis</hi> we may ſee that <hi>Abimelech</hi> king of <hi>Gerar,</hi> made a law concerning
<pb facs="tcp:6120:12"/>this mattter, that whoſoeuer did touch the man or his wife to the breaking of wedlocke, ſhould die the death. Verily it may appeare to all (vnleſſe they be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blind) that we in the cleare light of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel, are far worſe in this matter, then they which were vnder the law of nature, before the law of God written was giuen for the gouernement of his people. But if ſuch as God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed his officers and miniſters on earth, to execute ſuch notorious offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and tranſgreſſers of his law, who ought to deal in the puniſhment of this ſin, as God himſelfe appointeth, &amp; not as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes canons peſtilently preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth: that is to ſay, to ſée whoredome &amp; adultery puniſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> death, as the Lord himſelfe willeth, &amp; not ſo ſlightly paſſed ouer &amp; looked vnto as at this day it is. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law we haue theſe words repeated twiſe for fayling, <hi>The man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth adulterie with an other mans wife, becauſe he hath committed allulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie with his neighbours wife, the adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and adultereſſe ſhall die the death.</hi> And how diligent executors of this law
<pb facs="tcp:6120:12"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magiſtrates &amp; people of Iſrael were, it appeareth in that they were ſo ready to put to death that innocent <hi>Suſanna:</hi> yea in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very law of nature, it hath bin after that ſame maner puniſhed, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> when we reade that <hi>Iudah</hi> contemneth his daughter in law <hi>Thamar,</hi> becauſe ſhe was an adulteres, (although he himſelfe giuing ſentence againſt her, knew not that he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſin with her) to be burned. But I know this iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t will not be liked of ſome, but it ſkilleth not, for I come not to pleaſe men, for if I ſhould ſo do, I could not be the ſeruant of God: this I dare ſpeake, &amp; to all, of what ſort &amp; condition ſo euer they be, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrength of gods ſpirit I dare vtter it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lack of diſcipline is the occaſion of this ſin, &amp; is in ſome ſort by wicked &amp; vngodly perſons eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it were defended, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it is but a knack of youth, a piece of good fellowſhip, or if not defended, yet the puniſhment diminiſhed, and the faultes leſſened now as in time hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it hath bene: for the ſcribes &amp; pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes affirmed that if a man kept his body cleane from actuall ſinne, he could
<pb facs="tcp:6120:13"/>not be an adulterer or fornicatour: and no maruayle though the people were eaſily induced both to receyue and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue this opinion. For beſides that it is plauſible to fleſh and bloud, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcribes and phariſees themſelues, the authors of it, were in thoſe dayes men of great countenance and eſtimation, euen as Abbottes and Cardinals in the Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, or (that I may ſpeake more fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly and playnely) like to our Lord Biſhops amongſt vs, yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their credit, Chriſt ſetteth himſelf againſt them, not onely ſhewing howe corruptely they had expounded the lawe, but alſo opening the true ſenſe &amp; meaning thereof. So that this is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that though the worlde account neuer ſo little of this wickednes, know you yet the Lorde eſteemeth both the thought, wiſhing &amp; the deed doyng to be great &amp; grieuous ſinnes, and there fore ſo expreſly hath forbidden it, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed ſo greuous puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for it. Not that I meane that hee which ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in thought, ſhoulde by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate bee put to death, as well as
<pb facs="tcp:6120:13"/>he that doth the filthy fact in body: for that were with the Pelagians, Iouia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, and Stoiks, to make ſinnes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, which opinion of theirs I vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſlike and deteſt. For in reſpecte of circumſtaunce, one ſinne may be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then another, and ſo deſerue a ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per puniſhmente, but to teach you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the truth of gods law, that you ſhould not think thoſe ſins ſmall, which Gods ſpirite accounteth verye great (and indéed, without repentance, make a perpetuall ſeparation betwéene the Lord and vs) and alſo to declare, that we ought hartily to wiſh, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to pray, that Gods lawe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his will, with as much ſpeede as might be, and in as ſtraight a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as he hath commaunded, might be put in execution, to the puniſhing of the wicked, and the comfort of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Neyther am I ignorant howe ſome both haue and will kick againſte this doctrine, thinking that though it were ſo ſeuerely puniſhed in the old law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Iewes, yet it ſhoulde not bee ſo among vs. To this I coulde eaſilye
<pb facs="tcp:6120:14"/>yéeld, if they were able to proue, eyther God himſelfe the Lawgiuer, to be mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: which is impoſſible, or elſe the law not to appertaine to vs, whiche I think they are not able to doetor elſe if they were able to preſcribe a better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of politike gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God him ſelf, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> author of al wiſdome, hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſet out, which were preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and blaſphemy intollerable, for by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> means fleſh &amp; blood ſhould be, if not exalted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maieſte of God, yet made equall vnto him. But ſeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are not able to proue any of theſe points, it remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that vnles they wil be iudged fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward &amp; obſtinate, they conſente to this truth, &amp; acknowledge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame. But they are ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yéelding to it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſpare not to ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues againſt it, For did not Chriſt ſay they, ſay to the woman taken in adultry, God thy way &amp; ſin no more, &amp; <hi>Paul</hi> did not kil with the ſword but exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate by the word, the ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous perſon at <hi>Corinth.</hi> Therfore for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, adultery &amp;c. is not ſo ſtraightly to be puniſhed as you would haue it. I will anſwere bréefely, and for breuities ſake I wil omit many neceſſary points
<pb facs="tcp:6120:14"/>in theſe two examples, which otherwiſe if I might ſtand long vpon, they were worthy of the noting, &amp; firſt for Chriſts example, thus I aunſwere, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> execution of the law for puniſhing adultery with death, did belong to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ciuil magiſtrate, now Chriſt was none, as plainly appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by this ſaying: Man who made me a iudge or a deuider ouer you, ſpoken to one that would haue had him to haue commanded his brother to haue diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with him: and again by that which he ſpake to <hi>Pilate,</hi> My kingdom is not of this world. So then becauſe Chriſt was not a ciuil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat, he would not take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to put y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in execution wch he had nothing to do with, withal teaching vs to, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our vocation, &amp; kéepe our ſelues within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds therof, &amp; this may ſerue for anſwere to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> example. Now concer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning Paules dealing, wee haue thus much to note, that there was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo far as canne be gathered, no Chriſtian ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, that might take vppon him to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute this lawe, in his full force, and yet rather then ſinne ſhoulde be vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and wickedneſſe winked at,
<pb facs="tcp:6120:15"/>
               <hi>Paule</hi> woulde vſe the diſcipline of the Church, &amp; deliuer the inceſtuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ouer to Sathan for a time. Would to God, that if ſo bee the Magiſtrate neglect his duetye in puniſhing this ſinne, in ſuch ſeuere manner as Gods law appointeth, yet wee mighte haue ſome Paules and Elders in euerye Congregation, that would vſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> force of the word, and ſeuerity of Diſcipline Eccleſiaſticall, to the beating down of this, and all other like horrible vices. But all this notwithſtanding, it is la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable to be conſidered, and no god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man can without teares behold, the fond and ridiculous puniſhment of this ſinne vſed in theſe dayes. To be pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in a ſhéete, or pinned in a blanquet, and to ſtand in the Church, or in ſome Market place, or carted thorowe the Towne, is the moſt gréeuous cenſure of all: and yet in my iudgemente, as good left vndone, for it is the beſt waye that can be, to make ſuch as haue little ſhame in them, to bes altogether paſt ſhame, I will not ſay altogether paſt grace. And yet this kind of puniſhment
<pb facs="tcp:6120:15"/>belongeth to the poorer ſort. If riche ones ſinne, they are puniſhed by the purſe, fortie ſhillinges for committing ſuch an acte is iudged a great puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If this be not a maintaining of ſinne, I know not what is. For what vicious or ſenſuall man is there, that wil léefe his diueliſh pleaſure, if he may achieue it for money. Beſide that they which are puniſhed after that maner, for want of the execution of gods lawe, fall often into one and the ſelfe ſame ſinne. So that ſinne aboundeth, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquitie raigneth ſo much, that wee in this age, are comparable herein in a maner, with all the former ages of the world, which ſurely in my iudgement commeth to paſſe becauſe that maner of puniſhing ſinne, whiche God hath preſcribed is neglected, and an other which man hath deuiſed, ſet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place and ſtead thereof. You ſée the abuſe hereof. Pray hartilye that God woulde redreſſe this, and all other abuſes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning yet amongſt vs.</p>
            <p>It followeth, <hi>Let euery man haue his own wife, &amp;c.</hi> By generall doctrine, is
<pb facs="tcp:6120:16"/>in theſe words deliuered vnto vs, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prouing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mariage doth belong to al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtates, ſorts, and kinde of men, as well miniſters as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people, contrary to that doctrine of Diuels, by papiſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, who forbid mariage to ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But as this place doth plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ouerthrow that their opinion, ſo doe manye other both Examples and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies in holy ſcripture, whiche for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyding of tediouſnes, I willinglye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. Onely one as general as this, I think good to rehearſe, in the Epiſtle to the Hebrues we haue this ſaying: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is honorable among all men, and the bed vndefiled, as for whoremo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers and adulterers God wil iudge, you ſée by theſe words (beloued) that in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles iudgement, mariage is hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable among all men, of what conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſoeuer they be, ſo that to forbid it in ſome, is great and gréeuous iniquitye, ſeing that God hath enioyned al, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue not the gifte of chaſtitye or ſole life, to vſe mariage, as a notable remedye to put away the act of Formeation, with the luſt or concupiſcence thereof. And as out of theſe wordes a generall leſſon
<pb facs="tcp:6120:16"/>is giuen to all to marrie, if it bee in the Lord. So a man cannot without gréef conſider the horrible ſinne, and without horror ſpeake of the deteſtable iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, that thoſe men (Papiſts I meane) haue fallen into, that haue ſhunned this meane, much leſſe by them done. What whoredom, adultry, fornication, yea ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dometrie, yea buggery and other filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that ought not to be named in the mouth of Chriſtians) hath ben by them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, their own Chrouographers &amp; hiſtory writers plainly declare, &amp; this fayng whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are made popiſh prieſts is too plain, <hi>Si non caste, tamen caute,</hi> that is, if thou canſt not liue chaſtly, yet take a whore wartly. It ſhal be beſt for vs all thoſe iniquities being ſet aſide, to imbrace Gods councell, as the onely truth, and to ſhun the other as procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the Diuell, the father of all lyes and liers. Nowe though the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand euery one to haue his own wife for auoyding of Fornication, yet is it not his meaning that mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages ſhoulde bee made in ſuche ſorte, as GOD himſelfe hath forbidden, that is to ſaye, that young Children
<pb facs="tcp:6120:17"/>may marry, without conſent of pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. for in ſuch caſes, the aduiſe, counſell, &amp; agréement of fathers, is of neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. It is wonderfull to ſee, to what kinde of vngodlines and diſobedience, the world in this behalfe is growne, for mariages are made without conſent or counſaile of parents, which is a plaine breach of Gods commandement. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor thi Father and thi mother,</hi> &amp; this wickednes is confirmed and increaſed in an other reſpect, becauſe young men thinke themſelues in this behalfe more at liberty then maydens or Damoſels, Indeed if they could proue themſelues not to be children, and by the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement not to be tyed to obedyence, as the other are, I could eaſily be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded therein. But our wickedneſſe in both theſe caſes, is far greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that of the Gentiles. For in <hi>Geneſis</hi> wee read, that <hi>Shechem</hi> after he had rauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed <hi>Dinah Iacobs</hi> Daughter (whiche fact was altogether vngodly) did deſire his Father to get him that mayde to wife. If Infidels and vnbeleeuers did this, how much more ought Chriſtians
<pb facs="tcp:6120:17"/>that profeſſe godlineſſe to accompliſhe the ſame? Surely <hi>Schechem</hi> had as great priuileges as any yong man can now lay for himſelfe: for beſides that he was a yong man, hee was a Lordes ſonne, &amp; as it ſhould ſéeme, the only ſon of his father, and yet woulde not take mariage in hand (though otherwiſe hee had committed a vilanous act) without his Fathers conſent and aduiſe. Now this is further to be conſidered in this caſe on the Fathers part. For as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> child may not marry without the parents a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing and liking of the ſame: ſo can not the fathers or mothers eyther en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force their children to make vngodlye mariages, or to hinder &amp; let mariages begun in Gods feare, As many doe at this day, that becauſe one of the parties hath not aboundance of wealth, or ſuch like, will not giue conſent to the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of their children. But rather they ought to labour that in the Lorde, ſuch contracts and mariages, may as much as in them lyeth, be furthered. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in theſe words, <hi>Let euery man haue his own wife, &amp;c.</hi> This is to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the Apoſtles mind is not to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence
<pb facs="tcp:6120:18"/>any to marry with Infidels, or of corrupt religion, vnhoneſt behauior, or ſo forth, but that they ſhold haue due conſideration of the parties to whome they purpoſe by Gods grace to ioyne themſelues, and that they ſhoulde tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly know their religion &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> becauſe mariage is not a ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for a day a wéeke, a month, or a yere only, but for tearme of life alſo. Surely to ſpeak my mind, I cannot without gréefe conſider the great diſorder and confuſion vſed in the world at this day in this behalf, for eyther the beauty is one cauſe, &amp; ſo they ſatiſfye their eye &amp; carnall luſt, or elſe mony or goods another cauſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king therby to content their vnſatiable minds. Now adaies neither religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor honeſty is in mariages demanded, but rather we aſke how fayre &amp; beautifull, or let me vnderſtand how much monye I ſhall haue. Verely for a man to haue ſuch conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in chuſing of a wife is not altogether euill, becauſe a man muſt chuſe him ſuch a one as w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whom alone, he can holde himſelfe contente, ſo long as they ſhall liue together, but to put thoſe things in the firſt place decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="tcp:6120:18"/>to ſuch men as we deale w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in theſe caſes, that we like beaſts rather ſéeke things tranſitory and vaine, I meane beauty, ſubſtance, wealth and ſuch like then their daughters and children, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we more eſtéem of the one then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other Beſide that, when mariages are made in ſuch ſort, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; godlines (as if a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or profeſſor of the goſpel, ſhould marry with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidel, Turke, Iew, or Papiſt) we tread vnder our féete Gods comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; wholy deſpiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of godly &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men. In the law it is ſayd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iſrael, concerning the Gentiles which inhabited the land y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to poſſes. Thou ſhalt make no mariages with them, neither giue thy daughter to his ſonne, nor take his daughter vnto thy ſonne: a reaſon is added. For they will cauſe thy ſonne to turn away from me, &amp; to ſerue other Gods. Then will the wrath of the Lord wax hote againſt you, &amp; deſtroy thée ſodainely, wherefore <hi>Abraham</hi> cauſed the eldeſt ſeruaunt of his houſhold to ſweare, that he ſhoulde not take a Wife vnto his ſonne of the daughters of the <hi>Cananits,</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:6120:19"/>he dwelt, but that he ſhoulde goe vnto his countrie, &amp; to his kindred, &amp; take a wife vnto his ſon <hi>Iſaac.</hi> The ſelfe ſame care we ſée to be in <hi>Rebecca</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſaac,</hi> for their ſon <hi>Iacob,</hi> and therefore after that ſhe ſéemed to feare, leaſt he ſhoulde take one of the Daughters of <hi>Heth</hi> to wife, and had vttered the ſame gréefe vnto her huſband, <hi>Iſaac</hi> playnlye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth his ſonne, not to take a wife of the Daughters of <hi>Canaan.</hi> And in the new Teſtament it is ſayd: Be not vnequally yoked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Infidels. O but ſay ſome, I can reclayme her from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beléefe &amp; vngodlines, to faith &amp; vertue. Indéede if thou were as ſtrong as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and as wiſe as <hi>Salomon,</hi> it might peraduenture ſinke into my braine, but if the ſtrongeſt and the wiſeſt were not able to reſiſt, how ſhal the weakeſt and the ſimpleſt be able to ſtande. This is reckoned as one of the greateſtreaſons of <hi>Sampſous</hi> ruine, for taking a wife of the Daughters of the Philiſtines. And this is accounted as one of the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt cauſes of <hi>Salomons</hi> fall, that hee tooke him many wiues of outlandiſhe women, and ſtrange nations, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:6120:19"/>turned away his hart from the ſeruice of the true God, after their falſe Gods. And this is iudged to be one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſins, for which God brought an vniuerſall floud vpon the whole earth, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants therof, For that the ſonnes of God ſaw the daughters of men, that they were fayre, &amp; they tooke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wiues of all that they liked. Let vs therefore beware, and learne now at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> length, to deale more warily according to Gods holy councell in this and other matters then heretofore we haue done. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more this is to be noted that in that the Apoſtle will haue euerye man to haue his own wife, and euery wife her owne huſband, that he doth vtterlye take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way poligamie or multitude of wiues at one time. A doctrine not vuneceſſary and vnfit to be treated of in this place, becauſe (as I heare ſay, &amp; I do in part beléue it) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there bee ſome in <hi>Kent</hi> doe defend the ſame. I can not ſpeake of this and other things ſo largelye as I would, becauſe I haue bene hitherto ſomwhat long. I wil ſay both concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this and other thinges alſo that follow, my mind bréefely. Whoſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:6120:20"/>doth defend this as lawfull and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, not only ſtriueth agaynſt the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Gods ſpirit, in this place deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, who ſayth ſingularly euery man muſt haue his own wife, not wiues, but alſo quite &amp; clean turneth vpſide down the firſt inſtitution of mariage, for god in Paradiſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy joining woman vnto man as a helper, ſaid: For this cauſe ſhall a man forſake father &amp; mother &amp; cleaue to his wife, &amp; they two ſhalbe one fleſh, not they three, not they foure, &amp;c. but they two. This is alſo to be conſidered, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the firſt breach of this ordinance began, not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of the faithfull, but in the wicked ſéed &amp; ſtock of curſed <hi>Cain,</hi> for it is ſaid in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> that <hi>Lamech</hi> (who came of <hi>Cains</hi> kindred) tooke ij. wiues, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the one was <hi>Adah,</hi> and the name of the other was <hi>Zillah.</hi> So that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> either put in practiſe to haue many wiues, or defend y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, are of <hi>Cains</hi> progeny, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, a frowarde, adulterous, &amp; wicked poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neither is there any reaſon, why they ſhould to this end obiect the examples of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarks, and godly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the old law be
<pb facs="tcp:6120:20"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of our ſauiour chriſt, for in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was a great ſinne &amp; infirmity, and had not the Lord in mercy, and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of Ieſus, who was the lamb, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of the world, blot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted out their ſin, they had felt the payne and puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wch is euerlaſting death. You ſee then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>poligamie</hi> or multitude of wiues, cannot ſtand by Gods word. Let mans wit ſuppoſe what it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, this only is the truth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord giue vs grace to imbrace and follow the ſame. It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, <hi>Let the huſband giue vnto the wife, &amp;c.</hi> Now y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle ſheweth how we ought to liue after wee be maried, &amp; firſt he laieth out a general doctrine of mutual beneuole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is of the dutye of the huſband toward the wife, &amp; the wife toward the huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, wheras ſome haue vnderſtood by due beneuolence, the debt of mariage, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is the ſatiſfying of luſt, it liketh me not, becauſe it is ſomwhat to narrow. I indéed iudge that this mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo to expound the ſame, for that it followeth preſently afterwardes, <hi>the wife hath not power of her owne body, &amp;c.</hi> But it will ſtande more agréeable with truth, if we ſay that to be inferred
<pb facs="tcp:6120:21"/>neceſſarily, as a particular poynt oute of the former, becauſe the Apoſtle here dealeth generally. For his meaning is that the huſband ſhould doe to the wife &amp; the wife toward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> toward y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other, al duties pertaining to mariage. To intreat of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, I can not at this preſent, neither if I could would occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſerue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is that, which <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there be betwixt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch a conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; vnity of minds that their prayers be not interrupted, by which worde, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> priuate praiers were then, &amp; ſhold now be vſed in priuate houſes, wch how much it is obſerued, let al iudge. I feare me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if houſholders ſhould be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to accounts in this poynt, they wold come very ſhort. For wheras they prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed morning &amp; euening at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt euerye day, it is a great matter with vs, if we pray once a wéeke in our houſes, nay I iudge ſome of vs neither praye in our houſes, nor in churches, but come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther only for faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſake, &amp; this appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth becauſe ther foloweth ſo litle fruit of our prayers. for if we prayed hartily God wold here our praiers willingly &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:6120:21"/>graunt our peticions effectually. But we aſke many things, and obtayne few things, the cauſe is, for that we aſk the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not aright. It followeth, <hi>The wife hath not power of her own bodie, &amp;c.</hi> The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is, that God hath ſo created man for woman, and woman for man, that they cannot well be one without the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vnleſſe it be ſuch, as vpon whom he hath beſtowed the gift of chaſtitie: that ſentence ſerueth alſo well agaynſt <hi>Poligamie,</hi> or pluralitie of wiues. For if the bodie of the man be ſo tyed to the bodie of the woman, that the one is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the other, it cannot be, that the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath authority to take more wiues, nor the wife to take more huſbands. It followeth, <hi>Defraud not one another, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be &amp;c.</hi> In theſe words <hi>Paul</hi> ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth a notable remedie againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſhew of holines, &amp; loue of ourſelues For Sathan many times pricketh vs with a ſhew of weldoyng, to thinke our ſelues to be defiled by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of our wiues, &amp; therefore cauſeth vs to leaue our vocation, and thinke of an other e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate: as we reade that many men, and ſome kinges of this realme, haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken
<pb facs="tcp:6120:22"/>their calling, left their wiues &amp; become religious perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: ſo many wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men haue forſaken the duties of marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, &amp; cloſed vp the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in vnreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous cloyſters. Beſides this, mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſuch, &amp; it is ſo much addicted to the loue of it ſelfe, that at Sathans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation, the man dothnot only neglect his wife, but altogether loath her, and likewiſe the wife the huſband: for theſe cauſes doth the Apoſtle ſo earneſtly &amp; diligently reaſon of the mutual ſociety and loue betwixt man and wife: as if he ſhould ſay, if married perſons purpoſe to lead a ſingle life, eyther becauſe they ſuppoſe it to be more holy, or els are pricked thereto w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſundry kinds of luſt, not contenting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary meane y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God hath appointed, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſider, that they are tyed one to the other by a mutuall band: the man is but onely the one halfe of his body, &amp; ſo likewiſe the woman. Wherefore they haue not free libertie, to part aſunder as they luſt, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they luſt: but rather they ought to weigh this, we cannot be one w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>outanother, we lack one anothers ayde, God hath ioyned vs together, to
<pb facs="tcp:6120:22"/>helpe one another, let vs therfore one ayd anothers need. If they go ſo far y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſeparate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, the Apoſtle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, firſt a mutuall conſent, wch is neceſſary, becauſe the continency not of one only, but of both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is haſarded. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it be but for a time, for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peruall chaſtitie is not in their power, but is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gift of God. Thirdly, that they doe not therfore abſteine from keeping company one with another as though y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> abſtmence were of it ſelfe a good &amp; holy worke, or a piece of Gods ſeruice, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may giue ouer our ſelues to better exerciſes, to wit, <hi>fasting and prayer:</hi> in wch words we haue to conſider, that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh not of euery ſorte of faſting, and euery kind of prayer. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernes &amp; te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perancie are kinds of <hi>faſting &amp; prayer,</hi> &amp; ſhold not only be dayly but alſo continuall. He ſpeaketh therfore of ſuch a <hi>faſt</hi> as is a publike and ſolemne teſtimonie of repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, by wch we turn away gods wrath &amp; vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or by wch the faithful prepare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to <hi>prayer</hi> when they take in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſom earneſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The ſame may be ſayd of <hi>prayer,</hi> as for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome calamity or miſery
<pb facs="tcp:6120:23"/>is nigh, or if ſome toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods wrath appeare, or when ſome matter of great weight &amp; importance is to be taken in hand, as the ordering of miniſters &amp;c. And ſurely the Apoſtle doeth worthily ioine theſe two together, not as though faſting were a piece of Gods ſeruice, but becauſe it is a preparation vnto prayer. For the bodie being by faſting ſubdued, the more willingly (by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of Gods ſpirite) ſubmitteth it ſelfe vnto the ſpirite, &amp; being both ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they poure forth more harti ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord. And therefore our ſauiour Chriſt ioyneth them together in like ſort, when he ſaith, <hi>This kind of diuils is not caſt forth but by faſting and prayer,</hi> Now the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theſe words of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, we haue a plaine ouerthrowe, of that popiſh doctrine of diuorce, <hi>a thoro &amp; menſa,</hi> that is to ſaye, from bedde &amp; boord. They teach that for ſundry cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and endes, a man may be ſeparated from his wife, at the table and the bed, &amp; yet the Apoſtle ſheweth, that ſuch ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration cannot be made, for any ende but for this, namely that they may giue ouer themſelues to faſting and prayer.
<pb facs="tcp:6120:23"/>Their cauſes are worldly &amp; fleſhly, but the Apoſtles end is ſpiritual &amp; heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. No leſſe vaynely and fondly do they deale in the whole matter of <hi>Diuorce:</hi> for whereas our ſauiour Chriſt maketh but one cauſe, and that is <hi>Fornication,</hi> they make nyne or ten at the leaſt: and wheras by the warrant of Gods word, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faultles party may marrie, if he haue not the gift of continencie (for by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of God, the adulterer and adultereſſe ſhould both be put to death, as before I ſhewed in the beginning, and the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is ſet free, the huſband being dead, from the lawe of the man, and the man from the lawe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wife, the wife being dead) by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popiſh canon law yet in this realme mainteined, it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe, that neither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſin is ſo grieuouſly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed as of right it ſhold, neither may the faultles perſon marrie, but as wel y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> guiltles as the gultie, yea though they haue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gift of chaſtity, enioyned to liue a ſingle &amp; ſole life, nay wold to god it were not a ſhrewd &amp; ſinfull life. Now it followeth, <hi>&amp; again come together, &amp;c</hi> though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apowle wil haue chriſtian me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; women for godly exerciſes ſake, to
<pb facs="tcp:6120:24"/>ſeparate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, yet he wil not haue that ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to endure ouer long, the reaſon is added, <hi>that Sathan tempt you not &amp;c.</hi> As if the Apoſtle ſhould ſaye, when ye take vpon you to abſtein long fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſociety one of another, and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is profered to Sathan to oppreſſe you, becauſe you take that in hand wch you are not able to performe: for ſuch is the imbecillitie &amp; weakenes of the fleſh, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one cannot long be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the other, and therfore you had need looke to yourſelues ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aduerſary wil leaue no corner vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought, nor any ſtone vnrolled, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke you to wickednes &amp; incontinency. Here we haue to learne that leſſon wch I touched in the beginning, namely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God requireth pure &amp; chaſt mindes, as wel as cleane bodies. And alſo we haue to note the malice of ſathan, who goeth about like a roring lyon, ſeeking to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour vs: if we conſider his force, hee is ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as a lyon, if we weigh his ſubtilty he is called the great &amp; olde ſerpent, &amp; can tranſlate himſelfe into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> likenes of an Angel of light: he ſpared not Chriſt, but tempted him immediatly after bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,
<pb facs="tcp:6120:24"/>&amp; therfore he will not ceaſe to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile vs, we had need therfore to be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber &amp; watchful, and to pray continually w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the diſciples for the increaſe of our faith, becauſe faith is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mean, by wch we muſt reſiſt, &amp; though his power be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted great, yet this ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar comfort we haue in the ſame ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures reuealed vnto vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is but a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, &amp; playeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> part of a tyrant, who when he hath gotten any people vnder him in ſlauerie and boudage, doth miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably torment the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But if we reſiſt him (the diuill I meane) and ſet our ſelues againſt him he wil flée far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, for his tyranie is exerciſed only vpon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of vnbeliefe: as for the faithfull, he is not able to touch the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out gods ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance and appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: he cold not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terinto a few ſooine, til Chriſt gaue him leaue. He could not touch the body and goods of Iob, til God ſuffered him: his power is not increaſed, nor the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth and arme of our Lord any whit at al a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated. It remaineth then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſet our ſelues in conflict &amp; ſkirmiſh againſt the diuil, we ſhrinke not, for then we lie ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be wounded. The Apoſtle hath in the
<pb facs="tcp:6120:25"/>
               <hi>Epheſians</hi> deſcribed <hi>Panopleian,</hi> that is to ſay, complet harneſſe of a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he appointeth euery one to haue their loynes girded about w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> veritie, hauing on the breaſtplate of righteouſnes, their feete ſhod w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the preparation of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of peace, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhield of faith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> helmet of ſaluation, &amp; the ſword of the ſpirite. Marke how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle armeth a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſouldier in the fore parts, &amp; appointeth him in harnes for his backe to defend y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>all: by which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirtt of God teacheth vs, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what valiant courage we ſhould be indued, when we come to ſkirmiſh w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the diuill: we may not in any caſe turne our backs to him, for then we lie ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; eaſily receiue his wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, but reſiſt him by faith, as I ſaid before, &amp; he will flee far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. The Lord indue vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> force and ſtrength of his ſpirit fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue, to w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtand Sathan, &amp; all his wicked te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, &amp; imprint theſe things in our hearts which we haue heard, to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of our ſinfull liues and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, to the glory of his name tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Ieſus Chriſt, to whom with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, be al honor and glory for euer and euer, Amen. Let vs pray.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6120:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
